## **Alex Bair**

○ Chapel Hill, NC alex-bair143@gmail.com ② alex-bair.com ☐ alex-bair

#### **PROFILE**

I'm a full stack software engineer with extensive experience in JavaScript, TypeScript, and Ruby. I leverage my engineering and project management backgrounds to deconstruct complex problems and drive them to resolution. I love learning & using new technologies, applying deep technical knowledge to solve difficult problems, and working on a team to build amazing applications.

### **EXPERIENCE**

#### Creator, Software Engineer, Willow 🛮

2024 - present

Willow (willow-cdc.github.io) is an open-source framework for creating change data capture pipelines. It reflects database changes to a cache in near real-time.

- Developed framework to simplify change data capture pipeline creation from 9 steps to 4 steps.
- Designed and constructed a custom connector to transform events from Kafka and send to a cache (KafkaJS).
- Resolved Debezium configuration issues preventing multiple pipelines from connecting to the same database.
- Ensured Willow functions when provided a minimum privileged database user, avoiding the need to provide Willow with superuser privileges.
- Architected and implemented a RESTful API, facilitating pipeline creation and teardown (Express).
- Built pipeline management UI (React, Material UI).
- Authored comprehensive technical case study (willow-cdc.github.io/case-study 🗷 ).

#### Software Engineer, Self-employed

2022 - 2024

Developed freelance and open-source applications including:

- Whirlpool Tool for collecting and debugging webhooks (DO Droplet, Nginx, Express, Socket.io).
- Media Watchlist A media tracking web app (Ruby, Sinatra, PostgreSQL, HTML/CSS).

#### **Project Management Specialist, Merck**

2019 - 2022

- Led cross-functional teams on a \$46MM capital project portfolio to increase vaccine supply capacity.
- Fostered a collaborative, friendly environment among team members while achieving business objectives.

#### Photolithography Process Engineer, Texas Instruments

2017 - 2019

• Developed detection/interdiction systems using in-house technologies, reducing material holds by 30%.



# BackendFrontendOtherNode.js, Ruby, Golang, PostgreSQL,JavaScript (ES6+), TypeScript,Git/GitHub, Docker, Linux, Bash,MongoDB, RESTful APIs, Express,HTML, CSS, React, Jest, HandlebarsApache Kafka, Debezium, Nginx,Sinatra, Minitest, Redis, KafkaJSObject Oriented Programming

#### **EDUCATION**

**Launch School** 2022 – 2024

Multi-year, mastery-based software engineering curriculum. Read more at launchschool.com/employers

#### Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology

2013 - 2017